If you've ever had an artery scan done
to find out if you have plaque deposits
in your arteries, then it would be
especially useful to know how much lower
your heart disease risk is if you
reverse whatever plaque exists. I mean,
we've discussed a number of times how
reversing plaque buildup in our arteries
can occur. So, why not translate that to
actual reduced heart attack risk?
Fortunately, this study does just that
by looking at 23 studies, some
randomized control trials and some not.
And the researchers took data from all
these studies to relate the amount of
plaque in the arteries with actual
cardiovascular events or MACE, a
composite of multiple cardiovascular
events and then predicted the amount of
cardiovascular event risk reduction
based on a 1% reduction in plaque. Now
although it is true that plaque buildup
is a major contributor to heart disease
risk, there are some nuances to even
that. For example, the actual lipid
cholesterol levels stuck in the plaque
is one consideration. But in addition to
that is the inflammatory profile around
the plaque because a major component of
a growing atheroma that's the uh plaque
deposit is the amount of inflammation or
immune cells that is drawn to the region
to exacerbate the issue. Now these
immune cells take up cholesterol
containing particles as well as deal
with cholesterol molecules directly but
can get overburdened and die off inside
the atheroma. This forms a necrotic core
that is highly inflammatory as more
immune cells are drawn to that region
and the plaque continues to grow. In
addition, this necrotic core
destabilizes the atheroma making it more
dangerous as pieces can dislodge and
lodge themselves in finer blood vessels
causing serious complications like
stroke. And as a final piece, the
thickness of the cap that cells place on
top of the plaque can distinguish the
risk as a thinner fibroic cap is more
prone to breaking than a thicker cap.
Now, I mention all that because while
the researchers are measuring plaque
volume, it doesn't necessarily take into
account some of the other factors that
may be different for you. However, this
gives an excellent average idea of our
reduced risk. So, what did they find? If
we pop open the data, we're looking at a
table that indicates the amount of
cardiovascular event risk reduction.
Remember, less chance of a heart attack
or stroke per 1% reduction in plaque
volume. If the numbers are below one,
that identifies reduced risk. So, the
far left are the different statistical
adjustments. If you're interested in
those nuances, you can take a look. But
uh for the most important numbers are
the first one and the last. The first
one identifies a statistically
significant reduction in risk of about
17% per 1% reversal of atheroma volume.
So plaque amount. However, that's an
unadjusted correlation meaning that it's
a simple correlation without controlling
for any other factors like age or study
duration and things of that nature. So
if we turn to the final row, the fully
adjusted model, we see that the risk is
actually a bit further reduced down to
about 19% reduction. So the relationship
is not only maintained when the
researchers account for starting LDL so
low density lipoproteins that contain
the cholesterol as well as account for
age uh study duration, blood pressure,
diabetes, smoking, baseline plaque
volume and the type of patient as in did
they have cardiovascular event before or
did uh nothing show up already. Now,
there's an additional nuance that we
should cover before we finish this out.
Before we do, this is uh an analysis
that included a lot of studies on
statins. And the researchers describe
some of the unique non-
cholesterol-lowering effects of statins
along with the three key features that
are linked to the best changes in
atheroma volume. I'm covering that in
the extended version of this video. If
you're interested, you can find it in
the Physionic Insiders along with all of
my work. A private podcast, live
sessions with me, research reviews, a
private engaged community, and more. The
link to join is in the description, and
I would love to have you aboard. The
thing is, with this analysis, they
included a bunch of studies with
different comparators. Meaning, studies
don't just compare the treatment groups
against nothing. Typically they compare
against a control group that is either
given a placebo an inert fake treatment
or in this case some of the studies
actually many of the studies compared
against lowd dose statins and other
lipid lowering drugs. The reason that's
a bad thing or also a good thing as
we'll see is because the delta or the
amount of clinical difference between
the main treatment group and the control
group is going to range from a big
difference if the control group is given
nothing to a smaller difference if the
control group is given a similar
treatment just at a lower dose that
muddies the calculations. Ideally,
researchers would separate the two
comparators to tease out the effect of
plaque reversal on cardiovascular event
risk if comparing against a pure
comparison. So, placebo or a dirtier
comparison, lowd dose therapy.
Unfortunately, that also requires a lot
more data. But the good news here is
that because we have mixed comparators,
the real effect may very well be greater
than 19% reduced risk per 1% reduction
in atheroma volume. In the end, where
does that leave us? The study indicates
that if you were to test your arterial
plaque and then reliably test it again
and notice a 1% reduction in your
plaque, you would be estimated to have
reduced your cardiovascular disease
event risk like heart attack by around
19%. Then the question is how do we
reduce our arterial plaque? Fortunately,
I have multiple reviews of exactly that
right here. I'll speak with you over
there.
[Music]